在上一节我们看了一个填充预言机攻击
In the last segment, we looked at a
padding Oracle attack that completely
breaks an authenticated encryption system.
I hope this attack convinces you that you
完全破解了认证加密系统。我希望这个攻击说服大家
shouldn't implement authenticated
encryption on your own cause you might end
不要靠自己实现认证加密，因为你可能
up exposing yourself to a padding oracle
attack or a timing attack or any other
已经暴露给了填充预言机攻击、时序攻击或者其他一些这样的攻击
such attack. Instead you should be using
standards like GCM or any other of the
相反地，你应该使用GCM标准或其它
standardized authenticated encryption
modes as implemented in many crypto
标准化认证加密模式，有很多密码库实现了它们
libraries. In this segment, I'm gonna show
you another very clever attack on an
在这节里，我会给大家讲一个聪明的攻击
authenticated encryption system. And I
hope after you see this attack, you'll be
它是针对认证加密系统的。我希望大家在了解这个攻击之后
completely convinced not to invent and
implement your own authenticated
大家不再自己发明和实现认证加密系统
encryption systems. But instead, always
use one of the standard schemes, like GCM
但是一定要用标准机制中的一个，像GCM或其它的
那么我想给大家讲的这个特别的攻击是针对SSH二进制数据包协议的
or others. So this particular attack that
I want to show you is an attack on the SSH
SSH是一个标准的远程安全shell应用
binary packet protocol. So SSH is a
standard secure remote shell application
它是客户端和服务端之间的协议。它使用秘钥交换机制
that uses a protocol between a client
and the sever. It has a key exchange
一旦双方交换秘钥，SSH就使用二进制数据包协议
mechanism and once two sides exchange keys,
SSH uses what's called the binary packet
protocol to send messages back and forth
between the client and the server. Now
在客户端和服务端之间来回发送信息
here is how SSH works, so recall that SSH
uses what we called encrypt-and-MAC. Okay
SSH是这样工作的，SSH使用加密和MAC
so technically what happens is every SSH
packet begins with a sequence number, and
技术上来说,每个SSH数据包以一个序列号开头
then the packet contains the packet
length, the length of the CBC pad, the
这个数据包包含数据包长度，CBC填充长度
actual payload follows, then the CBC pad
follows. Now this whole red block here is
然后是有效数据，接着是CBC填充。现在整个红色块
CBC encrypted also with a chained IV, so
this is also vulnerable to the CPA attacks
使用带有链式IV的CBC加密的，因此这对我们之前所讨论的CPA攻击是很脆弱的
that we discussed before. But
nevertheless, this whole red packet is
但是整个红色的数据包
encrypted using CBC encryption. And then
the entire clear text packet is MAC-ed.
是用CBC加密的。然后计算整个明文的MAC
And the MAC is sent in the clear, along
with the packet. So I want you to remember
MAC以明文形式和数据包一起发送。因此我想让大家记住
that the MAC is computed over plain text
packets, and then the MAC is sent in the
MAC是根据明文数据包计算的，并且MAC是以明文形式发送的
clear. This is what we call encrypt-and-MAC.
And we said that this is not a good
这就是我们所说的加密和MAC。我们说过这不是一个好方法
way to do things, because MACs have no
confidentiality requirements. And by sending
因为MACs没有保密性要求。
the MAC of the clear text in the clear,
you might be exposing information about
通过明文形式发送明文信息的MAC，你可能会暴露明文的相关信息
the clear text. But this is not the
mistake that I want to show you here. I
但是这不是我想给大家看的错误
want to show you a much more clever attack.
So first, let's look at how decryption
我想给大家看的是一个更聪明的攻击。首先，我们来看看SSH如何解密
works in SSH. So what happens is, first of
all, the server decrypts the encrypted
首先，服务器只解密加密数据包
packet length field only. So it only
decrypts these particular first few bytes.
的长度域。那么它直接解密特定的开头几个字节
Then it will go ahead and read from the
network, as many bytes as specified in the
然后它会从网络读取和数据包长度域规定的字节数相同的数据
packet length field. It's gonna decrypt the
remaining cipher text blocks using CBC
它会使用CBC解密剩余的密文
decryption. Then, once it's recovered the
entire SSH packet, it will go ahead and
一旦，它恢复了整个SSH数据包，它会开始
check the MAC of the plain text, and
report an error if the MAC happens to be
校对明文的MAC，如果MAC是无效的，它会报告一个错误
invalid. Now the problem here is that the
packet length field is decrypted and then
现在问题是数据包长度域被解密
used directly to determine the length of
the packet before any authentication has
并且直接被用来决定数据包的长度，这之前没有任何认证
taken place. In fact, it's not possible to
verify the MAC of the packet length field
事实上，认证数据包长度域的MAC是不可能的
because we haven't recovered the entire
packet yet and as a result we cannot check
因为我们还没有恢复整个数据包，所以我们不能校对MAC
the MAC. But nevertheless the protocol uses
the packet length before verifying that the MAC
但是SSH协议在验证MAC之前就使用数据包
is valid. So it turns out this introduces a
very, very cute attack. And I'm only
结果是这引入了一个非常聪明的攻击
gonna describe a very simplified version
of this attack, just to get the idea
我只讲一个这个攻击非常简化的版本，来让大家理解
across. So here's the idea. Suppose the
attacker intercepted a particular cipher
下面我来说这个攻击。假定攻击者截获了一个特定的密文分组
text block, namely the direct AES
encryption of the message block M. And now
也就是直接用AES加密的明文分组M
he wants to recover this M. And I
emphasize that this intercepted
并且他想要恢复M。我强调一下
cipher text is only one block length.
It's one AES block. So here's what the
这个被截获的密文正好是一个分组长度，是一个AES分组。那么攻击者
attacker is gonna do. Well, he's gonna
send a packet to the server that starts
要做的是，他会发送给服务器发送一个数据包，这个数据包的开头是正常的
off as normal. It's basically, starts off
with a sequence number and then he's going
是以一个序列号开头。接下来他会
to inject his captured cipher text as the
first cipher text block that's sent to the
注入他截获的密文，作为第一个密文分组，把它发送给服务器
server. Now, what is the server going to
do? The server is gonna decrypt the first
现在，服务器会做什么呢？服务器会解密
few bytes of this first AES block and he's
going to interpret the first few bytes as
第一个AEC分组的开头几个字节，攻击者会截获开头这几个字节
the length fields of the packet. The next
thing that's gonna happen is, the server
作为数据包的长度域。接下来要发生的是
is gonna expect this many bytes, before it
checks that the MAC is valid. And so what
服务器会期待这些字节，在此之前不进行校验MAC是否有效
the attacker is gonna do, is, he's gonna
feed the server one byte at a time. So the
并且攻击者会每次给服务器发送一个字节
server will read one byte, and then
another byte, and then another byte.
服务器也会一个字节一个字节的读
Eventually, the server will read as many
bytes as the length field specifies, at
最终，服务器读够了和长度域规定的字节数相同的字节
which point, it will check that the MAC is
valid. And of course, the attacker was
这时候，它会校验MAC是否有效。当然，攻击者
just feeding the server junk bytes. And as
a result, the MAC is not gonna verify, and
只给服务器发送垃圾字节，结果，MAC就不会被认证
the server will send a MAC error. But you
realize that what happened here, the
服务器就会报MAC错误。但是大家意识到
attacker was counting how many bytes it
sent to the server. And so it knows
攻击者在数他给服务器发送了多少字节。
exactly how many bytes were sent at the
time that it receives the MAC error from
他确切地知道，当他收了多少来自服务器的MAC错误，他就给服务器发送了多少字节
the server. So that tells it that the
decryption of the first 32 bits of its
这告诉了攻击者，密文C的前32比特的解密
cypher text C are exactly equal to the
number of bytes that were sent before it
是严格等于在他收到MAC错误之前，已经发送的字节数
saw the MAC error. So this is a very
clever attack. So let me say it one more
因此这是一个非常聪明的攻击。我再说一遍
time to make sure this is clear. So again,
the attacker has a one block cipher text C
确保大家清楚。攻击者有一个密文C的分组
that it wants to decrypt and let's pretend
that when C is decrypted the 32 most
他想解密c，我们假定C解密后，得到明文的高32位
significant bits of the plain text happen
to be the number five. In this case, what
这个数字是5，在这种情况下
the attacker will see, is the following
behavior. The server is gonna decrypt the
攻击者会看到如下的事情，服务器会解密
challenge block c and he's gonna obtain
the number five as the length field. So,
挑战分组c，会得到数字5，并把5当作长度域
now, the attacker is gonna feed the server
one byte at a time and after the attacker
那么现在，攻击者会给服务器一次一个字节
feeds the server five bytes the server
says, hey, I've just recovered the entire
在攻击者给服务器5个字节后，服务器说“我刚刚还原了整个数据包”
packet, let me check the MAC. The MAC is
likely to be false and, then, it will
让我检查MAC，MAC很可能是错的
send, bad MAC error. So after five bytes
are read off the network the attacker is
服务器会发送一个坏MAC的错误，那么在读了5个字节后
gonna see a bad MAC error and then the
attacker learns that the most significant
攻击者会看到一个坏MAC的错误，然后攻击者就知道了解密后的分组的高32位
32 bits of the decrypted block is equal to
the number five. So there. So, you just
等于数字5，那么你就知道了
learned the 32 most significant bits of
C. So this is a very significant attack,
C的高32位，那么这是一个非常重要的攻击
because the attacker just learned 32 bits
of the decrypted cipher text block. And
因为攻击者刚刚知道了密文分组解密后的高32位
since he can apply this attack to any
cipher text block he wants, he can
他可以对任何他想要的密文分组实施这个攻击
basically learn the first 32 bits of every
cipher text block in a very long message.
他可以知道一条长信息的每个密文分组的高32位
So what just happened here? Well, there
are actually two things that were wrong in
那么这里发生了什么？密码设计里面有两个错误
this design. The first one is the
decryption operation is non-atomic. In
第一个是，解密操作不是原子操作
other words, the decryption algorithm
doesn't take a whole packet as input, and
换句话说，解密算法不取整个数据包作为输入
respond with a whole plain text as output,
or with the word reject. Instead, the
而返回整个明文作为输出，或者返回拒绝
decryption algorithm partially decrypts
the cipher text, namely to obtain the
解密算法部分地解密了密文
length field, and then it waits to recover
as many bytes as needed and then it
获得了长度域，然后等待指定数量的字节去还原
completes the decryption process. So these
nonatomic decryption operations are fairly
然后完成了加密过程，这些非原子解密操作是很危险的
dangerous, and generally, they should be
avoided. In this example, this nonatomic
一般来说，需要避免使用他们，在这个例子里，这个非原子操作。
decryption happens to break authenticated
encryption. The other problem that
正好破坏了认证加密，另一问题是
happened is that the length field was used
before it was properly authenticated. And
在正确认证之前，就使用了长度域
this is another issue that should never be
done. So the encryption field should never
这是另一个错误之处，不应该这么做的，所以加密的数据用不应该被使用
be used before the field is actually
authenticated. So let me ask you, if you
在这个域在被正确认证之前，我来问一下大家
had the option of redesigning SSH what is
the minimum change that you would do to
如果大家可以重新设计SSH，如何最小地改动这里
make SSH resist this attack? And let me
tell you that multiple answers might be
可以让SSH能抵抗这种攻击？我告诉大家，有很多种可能的答案
correct. One option is to send a length
field in the clear, just as in the case of
一个方案是，以明文形式发送一个长度域，就像TLS一样
TLS. In this case, there's no opportunity
for an attacker to submit chosen cipher
这样，攻击者就没有机会提交选择密文攻击了
text attack, because, well, the length
field is never decrypted. And so there's
因为长度域不会被加密
no decryption taking place that the attacker
can abuse. Replacing encrypt-and-MAC
这样攻击者无法滥用解密操作
by encrypt-then-MAC doesn't have any
impact because this attack would apply
采用“先加密后MAC”而非“解密且MAC”并无影响，因为这个攻击对于两者都是可行的
either way. The problem is that the length
field is used before it's authenticated
问题在于，在认证之前，长度域被使用了
and that would have to happen either way.
So a better mode of encryption doesn't
另一种方式也会出现这种情况，所以更好的加密模式并没有什么用处
另一种方法是单调对长度域计算MAC
actually help. Another option is to MAC
the length field separately so that now
这样服务器可以读去长度域，检查仅为长度域服务的MAC是否有效
the server can read the length field,
check that the MAC for just the length
然后服务器就知道了接下来要读多少个字节
field is valid, and then it would know how
many subsequent bytes to read before
之后再检查整个数据包的MAC域，最后一种方案是可行的，
checking MAC field on the entire packet.
The last option is actually one that
但是效率极差，可能会让服务器遭受拒绝服务攻击，
works, but is terribly inefficient, and it
would expose the server to a denial of
所以我不认为这是一个有效的答案
service attack, so I'm not going to mark
it as a valid answer. So the main lesson
需要记住的主要的教训是，不要自己去实现或设计自己的认证加密系统
to remember is, don't implement or design
your own authenticated encryption system.
只使用类似于GCM的密码学标准，但如果出于某些原因
Just use the standards like GCM. But if
for some reason, you can't use the
你不能使用标准，必须实现自己的认证加密系统
standards, and you have to implement your
own authenticated encryption system, then
那么请先加密后MAC，确保不犯这两节里的错误
use encrypt-then-MAC. And make sure not
to repeat the mistakes of the last two
也就是不在认证长度域之前就使用长度域
segments, namely don't use a length field
before the length field is authenticated.
更一般地，不在认证前使用任何解密的域
And more generally, don't use any
decrypted field before that field is
那么我们对认证加密的讨论完结了
authenticated. Okay so this is the end of
our discussion of authenticated
我想指出几篇关于认证加密的论文
encryption. I wanted to point out a couple
of papers on authenticated encryption that
你们可以进行进一步的阅读，第一篇文章很敏锐
you could use as further reading. The
first one is a very cute one on the order
是关于加密和认证的先后顺序的，讨论了是该先加密后MAC
of encryption and authentication that talks
about whether one should do encrypt-then-MAC
还是先MAC后加密，它证实了一个是正确的
or MAC-then-encrypt and it
shows that one is correct and one is
另一个是错的。这个文章指的一读，信息量很大
incorrect. It's a good read and there's a
lot of information in that paper. The
第二篇讨论了OCB模式，OCB是一个非常有效的
second discusses OCB mode, which is a very
efficient way of building authenticated
构建认证加密的方法。特别地，这篇文章看了一个带关联数据OCB的变种
encryption. In particular, it looks at a
variant of OCB with associated data as we
正如我们所讨论过的。最后三篇是关于攻击的论文
discussed when we described OCB. The last
three papers are attack papers. The first
第一篇描述上节讨论的填充预言机攻击
one describes the padding oracle attack
that we discussed in the last segment.
这篇描述了这节讨论的长度攻击
This one here describes the length attack
that we just described in this segment.
最后一篇描述了很多对加密机制的攻击
And the last one describes a number of
attacks on encryptions that just use CPA
其中加密机制只用了CPA安全，没有加完整性。最后一篇提供了很多好例子
security without adding integrity. So this
last paper actually provides a number of
解释了为什么CPA安全本身永远不应该被用于加密
good examples for why CPA security by
itself should never, ever, ever be used
记住，大家只能使用认证加密
for encryption. Remember the only thing
you're allowed to use is authenticated
来保护私密性。如果大家只需要完整性，不需要私密性
encryption for confidentiality. Or if all
you need is integrity with no
那么使用MAC就行了
confidentiality then you just use a MAC.